<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse concerning schools and school-masters offered to publick consideration / by M.N.</title>
            <author>Nedham, Marchamont, 1620-1678.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52756</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N387</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R308</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12409242</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12409242</idno>
            <idno type="VID">61469</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52756)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 61469)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 284:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse concerning schools and school-masters offered to publick consideration / by M.N.</title>
                  <author>Nedham, Marchamont, 1620-1678.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for H.H.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1663.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Written by M. Nedham. Cf. Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Harvard University Libraries.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Education --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:61469:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:61469:1"/>
            <p>A DISCOURSE Concerning SCHOOLS And School-Maſters Offered to publick Conſideration.</p>
            <p>By <hi>M. N.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>H. H. Anno Dom.</hi> 1663.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:61469:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:61469:2"/>
            <head>A Diſcourſe concerning <hi>Schools,</hi> and <hi>School-Maſters,</hi> Offer'd to publick Conſideration.</head>
            <p>THat the <hi>Education</hi> of Youth is one of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt concernments of the Nation, is a Truth ſo obvious to every ordinary underſtanding, that I ſhall not need to inſiſt upon the proof of it. Since 'tis plain, that the <hi>Scholaſtick State</hi> lays the ground-work and foundation of the other three States, <hi>viz. Oeconomical, Eccleſiaſtical,</hi> and <hi>Political;</hi> wherein the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties take their meaſures of goodneſs and felicity, from the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of thoſe Methods which were uſed and that ſucceſs which hath bin obtained in Schools; all perſons generally behaving themſelves in their ſeveral ſtations, (which providence fixes them in) according to thoſe Principles their childhood was firſt ſeaſon'd with, and that improvement of parts and manners they brought from thence. What is it that furniſhes Families with dutiful children, induſtrious ſervants, diſcreet Maſters? that ſupplies the Church with able Teachers, devout Hearers? that keeps Subjects in obedience to their Prince, in a quiet and juſt demea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour towards one another; but the powerful impreſſions of an early Inſtitution, which being once well ſettled grow into ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits, and become cor-natural to the temper and very conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the mind, not to be removed without great violence, and the continued efforts of ill company and conſtant debauches or diabolical infuſions. Again, 'tis no leſs obſervable, that 'tis eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mans care and main deſign, to provide well for his children after him, and to tranſmit happines to his poſterity: and this care is viſible enough in their leaving honors and eſtates many times purchaſed with their own diſquiet and ſin to boot. Now let me ask, what thoſe Legacies of the Parents love will avail, what the laws themſelves, which by bounding property are to ſecure thoſe eſtates to them, will ſignifie; if our Children that are to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed us, are not rightly principled in Piety and Obedience and the rules of honeſty, &amp; ſo prepar'd to a due obſervance of thoſe Laws; which if not kept by them as well as us, all our care &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion for them wil come to nought, and the next age that treads
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:61469:3"/>
upon our heels, if let looſe to licentious or factious practices and opinions, cannot but ruine all the benefits of our Peace, and the intereſts of our Religion; with this advantage, that their Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours muſt bear the blame of thoſe miſcarriages which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from a neglected education of their children. Nay, I ſhall appeal to the Story of our late villanous changes, whether a few phanatick ill-principled ſpirits may not get partly power to deſtroy, partly credit to corrupt the reſt of their fellow ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects from known rules of duty; as frequently thoſe currs, which ſpend upon a wrong ſcent, are apt to miſlead the whole pack.</p>
            <p>This being, as it is amongſt all men, who guide themſelves by reaſon, agreed on; It may juſtly provoke the admiration of any conſidering perſon, that all ſorts of people ſhould be ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs in this point, that amongſt other proviſions they ſeem to look upon education as the leaſt neceſſary, and think that charge loſt which is ſpent in breeding their children; which their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream laviſhneſs on other occaſions and their ſordid thrift in this doth abundantly teſtifie.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Res nulla minoris</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Conſtabit Patri, quàm Filius.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nothing ſhall ſtand the thrifty Dad</l>
               <l>In leſs then th' breeding of his Lad.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Not to mention thoſe of quality, &amp; take notice only of the rabble we meet with in the ſtreets; it muſt needs pity any Chriſtian heart to ſee the little dirty Infantry, which ſwarms up and down in Alleys and Lanes, with curſes and ribaldry in their mouths, and other ill rude behavior, as if they were intended to put off their humanity, and to degenerate into brutes. What hopes may we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertein of poſterity, when the better ſort are ſent over to forreign Schools of vice, to learn faſhions, to court miſtreſſes, dance <hi>à la mode</hi> and ſwear with a grace; and the worſer ſort are ſent no whither, but learn to imitate and outdo thoſe ſorry examples they have at home.</p>
            <p>Nor is this neglect to be charged only upon particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in their private ſphere; but the publick alſo may be thought to partake in the ſame guilt: when we conſider 'tis the only way to aſcertain to our poſterity the fruits of our late bleſſed and wonderful Reſtauration, and that ſo little has bin done towards it, and that that little too has bin ſo little look'd after and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd. Indeed it muſt be confeſs'd, that the Publick Counſels have
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:61469:3"/>
in the main bin very worthy and juſt and induſtrious in order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the great concerns of our peace, and in re-eſtab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſhing the Church in its antient Revenue and Reverence. And ſomthing by the by has bin toucht at for the Catechizing of Youth, for the Maſters abjuration of Covenant and ſubſcription to Church Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. But that either ſo imperfectly worded, as to afford an eaſie evation; or ſo poorly put in execution through negligence or corruption of Officers, that the law had as good never bin made. I do not ſpeak this with any imputation to the Henourable Aſſembly of <hi>Parliament;</hi> but with ſome reſentment of this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advertency bewail the fate of Schools, (which either have no patrons or their patrons no will to aſſiſt &amp; promote their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments) and pity the condition of poſterity, which is no neerer lookt to, no better provided for. It muſt be acknowledged, our worthy Patriots have buſineſs enough before them, to fill their hands and hearts, to take up their thoughts, and to imploy their diſcourſes. But when I find grievances of a meaner alloy conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered and redreſſed; I could not but conclude, that they would in their wiſedome have judg'd (had there ſtood up any one to repreſent) School-grievances and fraud and cozenage in that Myſtery of as great and ill a Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to the publicke, and as worthy their debate and a ſpeedy remedy as many of thoſe which are come into Acts. Whereupon in the ſilence of all others, I thought my ſelf obliged to take notice of this ſubject, and rather to extimulate ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who being better acquainted with theſe things may make out further diſcoveries, then out of any confidence of an ability in my ſelf to ſpeak much to purpoſe in a thing of ſuch moment, I have adventured to tender to publick conſideration my unpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed thoughts concerning the ordering of Schools to the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and improvement of Youth, and the advancement of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Religion.</p>
            <p>And firſt, to ſpeak of <hi>Stipend:</hi> reward being the very life of action, and the main incouragement of diligence.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quis enim vir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>utem amplectitur ipſam, praemia ſi tollas?</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For who imbraces virtue's ſelf, If you take away the pelf?</l>
            </lg>
            <p>'Tis the Salary which makes Schools and Learning flouriſh. <hi>Chi ben paga ben impara,</hi> ſayes the <hi>Italian.</hi> The conſcience of doing publick ſervice, and ſatisfaction of diſcharging ones duty, is not a ſufficient recompence for the toil of teaching. In Courts
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:61469:4"/>
of Law and equity no under-Clerk or inferiour Officers place, but may vie, for the profits of it, with the faireſt penſion of any publick School. Miniſters themſelves, who inſtruct us to expect fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture rewards, yet without a fair preſent maintenance would fall into the contempt of the vulgar, and their labours prove ineffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual. And this is the caſe of Schools: no imployment more publickly uſeful, none more toylſome and painful; yet no one more ſleighted even to reproach; no one leſs rewarded or regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. 'Tis a great ſcandal to the Nation, and certainly as great a grievance (if rightly conſidered) that no one ſort of men are greater ſufferers in this kind, then Schoolmaſters. Yet this muſt be ſaid in commendation of our Anceſtours, that their proviſion was very competent, and that the indowment of Schools was in proportion to the eſtates of thoſe times very fair and honorable. When workmen wrought for a penny a day; when that Land which is now worth 40. or 50. <hi>s.</hi> an Acre, was then thought a dear bargain at ten groats; when every thing was cheap but money; forty pound <hi>per Annum</hi> was a fair livelyhood, and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then, then 200. <hi>l.</hi> now perhaps. But what do we add to our forefathers ſtock? The Truſtees and Governours in the ſeveral Corporations ſhare the Improvements amongſt themſelves, take all above the Salary for lawful prize, and leave the Maſter to the bare old allowance, notwithſtanding the vaſt increaſe of the old Rents. So that by this means Schools are become Impropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations, and lay men (ignorant fellows) run away with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements of Learning, &amp; receive the rewards of the Maſters induſtry. This abuſe would deſerve the <hi>Parliaments</hi> notice, and a ſevere account to be taken of the Revenues of Schools; which might be done by requiring all Maſters and Governours to give in a perfect Inventory of School-Lands, Houſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with their yearly value, and ſetling accordingly an honourable Salary up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Maſter, with reaſonable abatement for Repairs and the Charges of the Overſeers. This courſe would invite men of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent parts and abilities into School-work; whereas now 'tis made the Sanctuary of many idle inſufficient perſons, who have no hopes elſewhere; or by thoſe, which have any merit, deſign'd a ſtep to ſome Church-preferment. It cannot then be expected, as things are, that the Schools of this Nation (excepting ſome few, which are Illuſtrious, and of Royal Foundation) ſhould be in any tolerable condition.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:61469:4"/>Having taken notice of the mean ſupport and ſlender mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, let us next take a view of the <hi>Methods</hi> of teaching uſed in Schools; and ſee what diſorders may be met with in them. I ſhall not pretend to be able to judge and give definitive Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, what is the beſt method; though we ought to have that regard to Antiquity and the cuſtom of former times, that we are to be very tender, how we prefer our own novell conceits to their tried and approved uſages; and that we do conſtantly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to that method and way which their practice, back'd with publick authority, hath chalked out to us, till authority do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend another. They do almoſt in all Countries entertain the ſame Grammar, and go by a certain rule of teaching; <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpauter</hi> obtains in <hi>France, Alvarez</hi> in <hi>Spain;</hi> and all <hi>England</hi> over heretofore, <hi>Lilly</hi> and <hi>Camden</hi> were in the hands of Youth. And indeed there is the ſame reaſon for <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi> in School, as in Church: the variety of Methods (ſuppoſing they were all ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verally in themſelves very good) doing very much miſchief, by not only diſtracting young heads, and diſcouraging them, and putting them back upon their removes to new Maſters; but alſo making a fundamental difference in their courſe as they proceed to other ſtudies. I have heard that a Biſhop, at an examination in a publick School, receiving an anſwer out of the common road, from a child, which had come lately from a private School, made this Reply, <hi>What,</hi> ſays he, <hi>Puritaniſm in Schools too?</hi> And ſo it is with us now, ſince theſe licentious times have overthrown all order, and broken us into ſo many ſects and factions; the Schools have been infected with that Fanatick Itch, and like In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent Congregations have bin variouſly adminiſtred by new Lights, according to the fancy of the ſeveral Teachers, that I dare ſay there are as many Grammars taught as there are Grammari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans to teach, if not more. It would be well if theſe loos brooms were gather'd again, if not into the old, yet into ſome one Model. 'Tis likely enough the old way may have ſome inconvenience, many defects and redundancies; why may not the ſame courſe be taken by us, as by the States of <hi>Holland,</hi> who upon ſuch an occaſion imployed <hi>Vaſſius</hi> to reviſe and mend and complete the old Grammars both Greek and Latine, which are now accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly read in the Low-Countrey Schools; or, for better ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, what if the <hi>Convocation</hi> would pleaſe to order ſome of their number, taking to their aſſiſtance ſome of the moſt able
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:61469:5"/>
Maſters, well experienced in teaching, either to correct what is amiſs in the old Inſtitution, or to draw up a new body of Rules and Syſtem of that Art, with the advantage of later inventions. It would be a thing not unworthy the care of Church-men, and that for which poſterity would pay thanks to their memory. Some eminent Divines in former ages have deſcended to that care, Dr. <hi>Collet,</hi> Dean of <hi>Pauls, Eraſmus, Card. Woolſey, &amp;c.</hi> In the mean time, I ſhall appeal to any man of ſober Judgement, whether it be conſiſtent with the Nations good, to baniſh ſchiſm out of the Church, and countenance it in Schools; and whether our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Youth, which is thus nurſed up in faction, is like to be well taught.</p>
            <p>When the Stipends and Methods are thus eſtabliſhed, I ſhould further propoſe, that there ſhould be no allowance for any one whatſoever to keep a <hi>private School</hi> upon his own account, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it be the Clerk of the Pariſh, whoſe office it ſhould be (with an allowance for it) to teach all the Children of the Pariſh at certain hours each day to write and reade, and that by the direction and under the inſpection of the Miniſter; and on Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turdays to prepare the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for their publick anſwering in the Church to the Catechiſe-queſtion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: and that when children are thus far inſtructed in their own Pariſh, they ſhould be then ſent to ſome publick School, unleſs the Parent were of an Eſtate to keep a Tutor (to be approved by the Biſhop) in his houſe, or were of ſo low a fortune, that he could not be at the charge of breeding his Child a Scholar. For without queſtion many of thoſe whif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling undertakers, that appear not in publick Stations, but ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture out upon their own private bottom, beſides that they drain the publick Schools, to their great hindrance and diſcouragement, Citizens being eaſily pleaſed with any thing that is new-fangled; may very well be ſuſpected to have no honeſt warrantable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, if they be well inquired into. I ſhall readily crave pardon of any one which ſhall be injured in that information which I have received; but muſt think my ſelf oblig'd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>in juſtice to the publick, to let it be underſtood, what ill offices may be done it (as I have heard) in private. There are at this time about the City ſeveral Maſters of private Schools, which have bin and are ſtill <hi>Covenanters, Presbyterians, Non-Conformiſts;</hi> ſome of whom have been outed out of their other mens places for Schiſm: who yet are incouraged by the confluence of youth from the City, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:61469:5"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the favour of ſome Noble Families: One at <hi>Clapham.</hi> One at <hi>Totenham</hi> High-Croſs. One or two at <hi>Chelſey.</hi> One or two at <hi>Newington.</hi> One at leaſt at <hi>Hackney,</hi> &amp;c. and ſo (as I am told) throughout the whole Kingdom thoſe of that party are deſigning the ſame courſe. Whether this be the fault of the under-Officers, a ſort of men that by ill execution of good Lawes have alwayes brought an <hi>odium</hi> upon the Epiſcopal Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, which imployes them, and the ſacred Order it ſelf, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which they depend: or whether it be the craft and cunning of thoſe Merchants of the Faction, who rather then ſit out will play any game, I am not able to diſcern; Authority may be ſatisfied, if it may be at leaſure but to make the inquiry. However, it hath a very ill face, and portends unluckily e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to the peace of the Nation, that there are ſuffered ſuch <hi>Seminaries of Faction,</hi> as if it were deſigned, that Poſterity ſhould retrive the <hi>Good Old Cauſe,</hi> and the Children ſhould car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry on <hi>the Work of the Lord</hi> in the following Generation, which hath proved too hot in ours (Thanks be to God) for the Father's fingers. Will not theſe ſuffering <hi>Brethren</hi> have a fair Opportunity of being revenged on the <hi>Reverend Fathers</hi> of our Church, for their ſeverity in turning them out of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt Livings, by training Youth to a contempt of Church-Authority and Order, and keeping on foot Nurſeries (like <hi>Barkſteads</hi> Regiment) of thoſe who may hereafter make up a Schiſmatical Army?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Lords,</hi> You had much better have continued them in the Pulpit; they will do ten times more miſchief now amongſt the Lambs, then they could have done amongſt the Sheep. What they did then, was like ſtealing of ſtanding Corn out of the Field, but rubbing the Ears; but what they do now, is ſtealing the Seed, the next years Crop, which the Civil Law hath determined to be a far greater theft. They have ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently ſpoiled the preſent Age, muſt they now be turned looſe to ſpoil the next Age too? If thoſe Spirits by their Religious canting could carry away Men and Women from their Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Father of their Country, and from the boſom of their Mother the Church, ah! <hi>My Lords,</hi> Are they to be truſted with the Children? I am of Opinion, that if the <hi>Vicar General</hi> would inſtead of School-Licences give them Licences
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:61469:6"/>
to practiſe Phyſick, he might doe the whole Nation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> good Office: For by this means, thoſe of their own Tribe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the onely perſons that would probably make uſe of them, they might in ſome reaſonable time give a fair account of the whole Fraternity; as we uſe to rid our houſes of Rats, by teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one to eat Rats fleſh, and then hanging a Bell about his neck he will never give over till he have ferreted all the gang away. In good earneſt, it would be more prudent to adviſe his Majeſty to allow all that have ſuffered in that kind, and are otherwiſe unprovided, (which will not be many) a mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Penſion out of his Exchequer, then thus to admit them to an imployment, which may be of ſo dangerous a Conſequence to the publick Peace. And whereas they pretend not to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmeddle with the Inſtruction but leave that to a little Officer, ſome puny Fellow they get from the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity,</hi> who may ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe according to the Act, while themſelves keep their own Conſcience free to the Godly Deſign: beſides, that it is plain enough what danger there is in their very Converſe and Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, in their Hums and Haws, in their Graces and Family-Exerciſes; it being ſo familiar with Men of that Principle, to ſow Sedition in their very Prayers, and to make Religion it ſelf a Stale to Faction: I ſay, beſides this, it will be found upon inquiry that they do too execute the Teaching Part, by ſpending conſiderable portions of their time in examining and taking account how their Children profit; though this muſt be ſaid in their behalf, that for their teaching of Letters there is not that fear of a <hi>Presbyterian's</hi> doing much miſchief, ſeeing it may be ſuppoſed they cannot be very comunicative of what moſt of them have not; but it is believed, it was the intention of that Act to take from them the Opportunity of ſpreading the Leaven of their Factious and Diſloyal Opinions, which they can more effectually do in the Duties of the Family: And it may be eaſily gueſſed by the Relations, on what errand thoſe Children are ſent to ſuch Maſters or Landlords, namely, that they may learn to fear God, and diſobey the King and the Church, (as their Fathers before them have done.) I am ſomwhat the more earneſt on this Subject, becauſe it muſt be confeſſed, that thoſe who were cenſured unfit for Church-work, ought to be judged much leſs fit for the work of the School: and if the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:61469:6"/>
Prieſts are denied to the Fathers, much more ſhould the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren be kept from them, unleſs we would verifie that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb, that <hi>The Fathers have eaten ſour Grapes,</hi> and now <hi>the Childrens teeth</hi> muſt be <hi>ſet on edge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To come then to the laſt and chiefeſt Conſideration; How <hi>School-Maſters</hi> themſelves are to be qualified, that they may laudably perform the great Truſt and Duty which is charged upon them. What difficulties the Work hath in it, to encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all kind of Tempers, and improve all ſorts of Wits, to be <hi>ingeniorum &amp; morum artifices,</hi> to faſhion Minds and Manners, to cultivate rude Soil, and diſpoſe Youth to Virtuous behaviour againſt their Natural inclinations; what cares and pains, what great abilities of Prudence and skill and all Virtue, what a Cycle of Knowledge it requires to inſtruct others in the grounds of Literature, to raiſe their Parts, to heighten their Fancy, to fix their thoughts, and to crane their <hi>Genius</hi> to the pitch, and ſo prepare them for publick Service, is a thing more eaſily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed then conſidered, more talked of then taken notice of. It is a great wonder of Providence, when we look on the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Conſtitution of Schools, how much contempt, and how little incouragement is ſhewn to the Profeſſion, that there are any able and worthy men of that way; and ſure whoever they are, it was at firſt not the ſpontaneous Election of their own mind, but ſome outward neceſſity of Fortune, or ſome other Fatality that condemn'd them to thoſe Galleys, and tied them to that Oare, ſeeing thoſe that are ingaged do moſt upon the ſtocke of their own credit work through the flint: So true is that,</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quem Jupiter odit, Paedagogum facit.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To whom a ſpite<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Jove takes,</l>
               <l>Him Paedagogue he makes.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Were Parents obliged but for ſome time to the trouble of inſtructing their Children, (they think it trouble enough to have them in the ſame houſe;) they would quickly be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced, what reſpects were fit to be paid to him, who under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:61469:7"/>
ſuch a charge, and what pardon he would deſerve at their hands for ſmall failings, when themſelves cannot ſecure them from great ones. But were the forementioned courſe taken, of proportioning the Salaries to the improvement of Rents, there is no queſtion to be made, but Schools might be well provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with gallant and able men, who might diſcharge that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional truſt with brave ſucceſs, and yet with great Splendour and much eaſe. Were that done, young Scholars at the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſitie</hi> would prepare themſelves for School, as for a handſome Prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; whereas now nothing but pure neceſſity can put them upon that way: They would practiſe to talk Latine fluently, that they might readily entertain any ſtranger, (which now many that have the Reputation of good Scholars are but clumſy in) and poure forth Verſes and Declamations <hi>extempore;</hi> they would ſtudy the Claſſical Authours thoroughly and digeſt them, acquaint themſelves with all the Critical parts of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lology, and the Elegancies of the Language, and the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms of Antiquity: How many <hi>Eraſmuſſes,</hi> and <hi>Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cthons,</hi> and <hi>Scaligers,</hi> and <hi>Puteans,</hi> and <hi>Voſſiuſſes,</hi> ſhould we have amongſt us in a ſhort time, if Literature were but thus encouraged? whereas now generally the Pulpit is made their ultimate Deſign; and when they ſet once a preaching, they lay their ſtudies of Humanity aſide.</p>
            <p>Before I part with this, I muſt not forget one thing, which I take to be a main Cauſe of the Maſters toil, and the Scholars non-proficience; that as Schools now are, the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter takes too much upon him, and more then he can poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly with any credit diſcharge: For you ſhall ſee in moſt Schools but a Maſter and an Uſher, and ſometimes but one ſet over a Company of Boyes, whoſe Capacities and Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies may be ſorted perhaps into ſeven or eight <hi>Claſſes.</hi> It is not poſſible one or two men, (let them work their hearts out) ſhould ſuffice to this Duty: Wherefore, if it were ſo ordered that every great School might have for each Form a Maſter, who might be as the Intelligence of that Sphere, and wheel it about with him through the whole <hi>Encyclopedy</hi> of School-Learning, (with a Rector or Preſident over them all) the work would go on with great facility and cheerfulneſs, and no leſs ſucceſs.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:61469:7"/>This is the courſe which the Jeſuites take, and which makes them look'd on as the greateſt Maſters of breeding up Youth: And this would be very feaſible, to have in every great Town almoſt ſuch a School, at leaſt one or two in a County. To inſtance. What were it for <hi>Kings-Colledge</hi> to ſupply <hi>Eaten-School, New-Colledge</hi> to ſupply <hi>Wincheſter-School</hi> with half a dozen young Maſters, who might, as they ripened each his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, return back to his Colledge, and there, if his Superiours ſhall judge fit, go on with thoſe that are taken for the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity,</hi> through the courſe of Philoſophy: And ſo out of <hi>Chriſt-Church</hi> in <hi>Oxford,</hi> and <hi>Trinity</hi> in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> ſeven or eight, or half a ſcore young men would not be miſt; who if they were imployed in <hi>Weſtminſter-School,</hi> which furniſhes both thoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Colledges, might by dealing the work amongſt ſo many hands make it very light and proſperous; and ſo of other Free-Schools, eſpecially thoſe that ſend Scholars to certain Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges.</p>
            <p>And this would be a pretty Introduction of young Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Arts and Batchelours into the World, and prepare them for a ſerious Scene of Action; and keep them from growing muſty in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſitie,</hi> where Colledge-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and the Walks, (if not good fellowſhip) indiſpoſe many for the Duties of an Active life; and to ſay Truth, what have they thoſe Fellowſhips and Allowances for, but to ſerve the publick, which they cannot do better at firſt ſetting out then in this way. And for places of leſſer note, <hi>Servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors,</hi> when they are arrived at Degrees, may be ſent to Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciate for a time appointed, and not have Orders preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly given them, and to be put to their ſhifts (as heretofore) in the Miniſtry, when their neceſſities recommended them to <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Families or poor populous Corporations, where for a livelyhood they ſtudied <hi>placentia,</hi> preached down the Church and preached up the Kirk: for it hath been obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that your factious little Chaplains, and the Lecturers of your great Towns proved the <hi>Boutefeus</hi> of our late Troubles. There being one or two ſuch Schools in each County, how eaſily will the Gentry fall in, how readily the other ſort of people, eſpecially if ſuch Schools have ſome Colledges in ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity</hi> allotted for their preferment upon ſolemn
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:61469:8"/>
Probations; which may be eaſily contrived without breach of any Statute. Nay, many Colledges we ſee are already ſo allotted, as thoſe I mentioned before: ſo Saint <hi>Johns<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> for <hi>Merchant Taylors: Jeſus Colledge</hi> for the <hi>Welſh: Exceter</hi> for <hi>Devonſhire</hi> men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and why may not the reſt be ſo ordered? And then for places of leſſer Note, as little Market-Towns, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> where there is great number of Children, and ſome that their Parents would wiſh ſhould do more then barely write and read, which we ſuppoſe is the Clerks work to teach them: there as was ſaid before, may be one or two meaner perſons with a leſs Salary, who may be ſtinted too in their work; ſo as to teach onely Latine according to Grammar-Rule: for thoſe who would deſign further, ſhould be obliged to attend the great Schools; and no other School ſhould have Priviledge to fit Scholars for the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſitie,</hi> by which means there would be a great concourſe thither; and if the Gentry were nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, there might be provided Maſters of other Faculties to take up their leaſure hours and intervals of ſtudy; <hi>viz.</hi> A Catechiſt, an Arithmetician, a Writing Maſter, a Maſter of Fence, a Dancing Maſter, Muſick Maſters, a Rider of the great Horſe; ſome old Souldier to teach them their Poſtures, and to handle their Arms, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And beſides this (which is the other advantage of your boarding Schools) the benefit of Aire might be procured, in the Summer quarter at leaſt, by removing two or three miles out of the Town to ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient ſeat, which might with thoſe Improvements eaſily be purchaſed; as alſo other requiſites provided for the eaſe and Reputation of the Maſters, and the benefit &amp; advantage not of the Scholars alone, but of thoſe Towns alſo where the Schools are kept. Nor would this Academical way tend at all to the diminution of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities,</hi> but much advantage them in their Repute, by certain conſtant Homages from all the Schools in the Nation, holding from them <hi>in Capite,</hi> governed by their Miſſionaries, and by their Rules; and at laſt accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their demerit upon Trial, expecting Preferment from them; to which Repute the mutual Emulation of the Maſters in their ſeveral Provinces being alwayes <hi>in Fluxu,</hi> and not Stationary; and the account that they muſt make to the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge which ſent them, would very much conduce. Now
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:61469:8"/>
thoſe Provinces or <hi>Claſſes</hi> might be ordered according to the ſeveral Stages, Scholars go in their School-learning, after ſome ſuch Draught as this:</p>
            <list>
               <item>The firſt <hi>Claſſe, Grounds of Grammar, declining Nouns</hi> and <hi>Verbs.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The ſecond, <hi>Congruitie of Latine.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The third, <hi>Proprietie</hi> and <hi>Phraſe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The fourth, <hi>Oratory</hi> and <hi>Rhetorick.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The fifth, <hi>Poetry</hi> and <hi>Verſe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The ſixth, <hi>Greek grounds.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The ſeventh, <hi>Dialect.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The eighth, <hi>Antiquity</hi> and <hi>Philology.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>But this Courſe may be left either to the Arbitrary diſcretion of the preſent Maſter, or elſe Regulated by the <hi>Head</hi> and <hi>Seni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors</hi> of the Colledge, to which that School ſhall appertain ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to occaſion.</p>
            <p>To make ſhort, this laſt <hi>Paragraph</hi> is offered as a <hi>Scheme</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon ſudden thought, on purpoſe to ſuggeſt to ſome more ingenious and better experienced Head, to find out an expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient for preventing the Maſters toyl, and yet aſſuring the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs: Nor hath the whole Diſcourſe any other Deſign, then barely to repreſent ſome inconveniences in the managing of Schools, which are very viſible to any one, but have not been taken publick notice of by any; not that the Writer of this is at all an <hi>Opiniator</hi> of himſelf, or hath the confidence of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truding his crude and undigeſted Senſe upon the great Council of the Nation, or hath indeed any concernment in the <hi>Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance,</hi> further then his own Children, whom he ſhall provide for, whether this have any effect or no; or can entertain any great hope to have this Paper conſidered or lookt on by any of thoſe who may be concerned in the <hi>Redreſs;</hi> much leſs was it in his aim to level <hi>Satyre</hi> at any one, any otherwiſe then honeſtly to diſcharge his own burthened thoughts, in reſentment of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:61469:9"/>
that which his mind told him deſerved to be the Object of a publick care, with the ſame Freedome as he thought them. And if any one find himſelf aggrieved at the Writer, he muſt not blame him for having a greater tenderneſs for the publick good, then for any private perſon; and withal let him take this Character of him, that he is one bears that love to his Country, that Faith to his Prince, that Reverence to the Church, and that Honour for all true Worth and Deſert, that he ſhall not be grieved himſelf to ſee his own Intereſt, his Reputation and deareſt Concerns lie bleeding for their ſakes; and will readily allow his forgiveneſs for any unkindneſs any one ſhall do him upon ſuch a ſcore.</p>
            <p>Much more might be ſaid concerning the Exerciſes, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuch as are to be performed publickly; and concerning the Diſcipline of Schools by reward and puniſhment: wherein I ſhould particularly adviſe that <hi>whipping</hi> might be, if not totally laid aſide, at leaſt very ſparingly uſed, and that upon Moral tranſgreſſions; as Swearing, Thieving, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and then too by the hand of ſome Servant, the Bedle or <hi>Lictor</hi> of the School; as an Office in it ſelf ſervile, not at all beſeeming either Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman or Divine to execute; or indeed becoming any thing of Ingenuity, either to act or ſuffer. Indeed the great indiſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and intemperance of Maſters in that, hath brought a very great contempt and hatred upon the Profeſſion it ſelf: and not to ſpeak of the ill uſe ſome have made of it to lewdneſs (of which Inſtances are not wanting, but that they are odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous) it being a kinde of uncovering nakedneſs: it doth ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally more hurt then good, by making thoſe that are dull more dull, and diſpiriting the ingenious; and truly, wicked Boys (to whom it properly belongs) are by the frequency and commonneſs of it hardened; and being grown after a while ſhameleſs, and ſenſeleſs of the Rod, having paſt the laſt remedy (as this is accounted) doe become incurable: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as ſuch are to be kept in a courſe of Diſcipline, as not to be mended with the moſt ſevere inflictions of preſent ſmart, which is quickly worn off.</p>
            <p>To theſe Heads, and other Expedients, I do not want ſtore of Obſervations taken up both abroad from other Countries, and at Home, in our own: but think it beſt to reſerve them
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:61469:9"/>
till ſome other time, if occaſion ſhall be offered. Again, I conſider, this is but a needleſs work peradventure: for when Salaries are improved, the Grounding Methods ſettled, and Maſters well qualified, as to their Abilities and Affections, theſe Maſters will in their ſeveral Companies for Superſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture and Diſcipline, and other Prudential wayes, better poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly conſult for themſelves, then any by-ſtander can. Let me add, that in that Method by me laid down, there is not any prejudice in the leaſt intended to thoſe Maſters, who are at preſent in Poſſeſſion of publick Schools; but on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary great advantage of Eaſe, of Honour, and of Profit. For ſuppoſing the number of Schools ſhould be reduced to that paucity there mentioned, out of thoſe Maſters might be choſen the <hi>Scholarcha</hi> or Rector of each School, and his Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leagues too, <hi>pro hâc vice,</hi> whoſe ſingle Forms would bring them in better returns, then their whole huddle of Scholars doth now. Thoſe of the leſſer note might be planted in the leſſer Towns, and nothing to their loſs. After theſe old ſtanders were worn off the Stage, then <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſitie</hi> men might take their <hi>Qu.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall Conclude with an humble Addreſs to thoſe in place and Power: (it being not impoſſible that ſome ſuch may chance to let fall their Eye upon this Paper.) That the <hi>Honourable Court of Parliament</hi> would, as they tender the Peace of three Kingdoms, and the preſervation of their own good Laws, lay to heart, and take into ſerious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration the neceſſity of wholſome Inſtitution for our Children; that they would give publick Schools a publick Countenance, and remove thoſe Grievances, which they labour under, by ſettling handſome Salaries, and eſtabliſhing ſome kind of Uniformity; That they would not ſuffer thoſe ſeeds to be ſcattered in the minds of Youth, which have in theſe late years produced ſuch a Harveſt of miſchiefs and confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; (upon this ground, that Royal Clemency is to be li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to Perſons, not to be extended to Principles:) That they would take up that Noble Deſign of <hi>perpetua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                     <desc>•••…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in a well bred Poſterity: and Laſtly, That they would not be ſlow in a Buſineſs of ſo great and quick Concernment;
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:61469:10"/>
the hopes of the next Age lying at ſtake, Children grow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing up into Men apace; and what is taken in now being hardly cured hereafter, the Elder ſort affording very few examples of Converſion. That eſpecially, the Right Reverend the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, would not onely provide for the Sheep, but take care that the Lambs may be fed, as the great Shepheard and Biſhop gives them Order: That they would in their Dio<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſes Viſit Schools, as well as Churches, and incourage Youth in Vertue: That they would pleaſe to uſe their Power for dete<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cting the Frauds of Truſtees, and for reſtoring to Schools thei Rights: And in fine, That they would injoyn their Ordi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>naries to be very ſtrict and careful what Maſters they admit how they are qualified, and affected to preſent Governmen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> both of Church and State: For he that is an Enemy of on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> can be no Friend to the other: And to call, eſpecially all pri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vate Teachers, and School-Maſters (what ever their pretenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> may be) to a publick Account; it being found a task al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>moſt impoſſible by all Methods the Church of <hi>England</hi> ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uſe to recover thoſe perſons to a ſound Orthodox Senſe whoſe Childhood hath been poyſoned, and prepoſſeſſed with Schiſm.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:61469:10"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
